All right, anyway, so today's דף *daf* is דף צ"ח *Daf Tzadik
Chet* and yeah, we're about to see the whole debate of, get
back in the debate of רבי אליעזר Rebi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* or
רבי יהושע Rebi Yehoshua, *Rabbi Yehoshua*. רבי אליעזר Rebi Eliezer. *Rabbi Eliezer*
says that they have to do תשובה teshuva *Teshuvah*, רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua, *Rabbi Yehoshua* says God will force it if necessary. So Micah
was asking about what if, but doesn't that mean that what do
you call it, that they all agree in principle they have to
do תשובה teshuva *Teshuvah*? You know, it could be the answer is
yes, but the question is what type of a תשובה teshuva. *Teshuvah*?
A תשובה teshuva, *Teshuvah* because somebody's holding a gun to your head,
right, or a תשובה teshuva, *Teshuvah* because you really, you know, are
sincerely on your own motivation? It also's a question about not just
at a personal level, but at a question about where the world
is at. You know, we're going to sort of get to the
opinion about like, does it have to be דור שכולו חייב *dor
shekulo chayav* or דור שכולו זכאי *dor shekulo zakai*? Like, you know,
it'll either come at a time when the entire generation is merits
or the entire generation is sinful. So that first of all seems
to be that if רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*, if that's
consistent with רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua. *Rabbi Yehoshua*'s approach is that they
don't have to do תשובה teshuva *Teshuvah*, right, that they could be
completely sinful. But even if they have to do תשובה *Teshuvah*, it's
a little bit different if because of an immediate threat, you know,
people are doing a, like, you know, everybody does תשובה *Teshuvah* on
יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* hopefully. Does that really mean that they've changed
and does it really mean that the world is a better place,
right? If you think that if you take a רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* approach, it's not just at the individual level people
have to do תשובה *Teshuvah*, but presumably it more means that we
have to bring about a Messianic period because we have to turn
the world into a more righteous world, into a better world. So
that could also be a question of like, how much is bringing
about Messianic period something that's under our control or something that's going
to come, you know, imposed upon us from God? So it's important
to think not just in terms of whether the individual's merit, but
if you take a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* approach, only
if everybody has done תשובה *Teshuvah*, the way means only if we've
transformed the world and made the world into a more righteous place,
right, so as opposed to if רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua *Rabbi Yehoshua*,
even if רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* thinks that, oh, God'll make them
do תשובה *Teshuvah*, it's not going to change the nature of the
world, you know, it's still going to be imposed by God. So
there still is a fundamental difference between how you sort of conceptualize
what that period of Messianic is going to be, yes.
Doesn't that involve just start violating all of הלכה
*Halacha*
to make it a דור שכולו חייב *dor shekulo chayav*? Yeah, I
think so, yeah.
So it could be in our power
to make a דור שכולו חייב *dor shekulo chayav*, yeah. We're doing
better at that than we are at this דור שכולו זכאי *dor
shekulo zakai*.
Let's try to align the debate of רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* and
רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* with that of שמואל Shmuel: *Shmuel* and רב
*Rav*, where שמואל *Shmuel* said, you know, that no תשובה *Teshuvah* at
all is necessary, right? So then how does this differ from...
Right, well, שמואל *Shmuel* just says די לו לאבל שיעמוד באבלו *dai
lo la'avel sheya'amod be'evlo*.
The way it was explained issues, he was a different take is
that שמואל *Shmuel*...
yeah, and then because no, because it's going to be enough and
the time is going to come, then God will bring משיח Mashiach
*Mashiach*. What's going to happen to make משיח Mashiach *Mashiach*? Maybe it
means that God will make everybody do תשובה *Teshuvah*, but it doesn't
seem like רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* is strongly committed to God will
make everybody do תשובה *Teshuvah*. That's not really the point. That's like
how do you reconcile various פסוקים *psukim*, but the point is God
is going to make it happen, okay, and it's not going to
be that we've brought the world to that state. Okay, so let's
take... we'll get to that later. Let's take a look at picking
up at the top of ninety-eight ע"א
*Amud Aleph*. I don't know exactly where I left you off, we'll
start from the top line. אמר ליה amre lih, רבי אליעזר *Amar
lei Rabbi Eliezer*, so רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* said to him, והלא
כבר נאמר אם תשובו ישראל Israel נאם ה' אלי תשובו *V’halo kvar
ne’emar Im tashuvu Yisrael ne’um Hashem elai tashuvu*, if you return to
Me... then... אמר ליה amre lih, רבי יהושע *Amar lei Rabbi Yehoshua*,
והלא כבר נאמר ושמעתי את האיש לבוש הבדים אשר ממעל למימי היאור
*V’halo kvar ne’emar v’shamati et ha’ish levush habadim asher mima’al l’meimei haye’or*,
I heard the person dressed in the cloak who was above the
rivers of the Nile, וירם ימינו ושמאלו אל השמים וישבע בחי העולם
*Vayarim yemino usmolo el hashamayim vayishava b’chei ha’olam*, he lifted up his
right and his left hand to the heavens
and he swore in the name of the One who lives forever,
כי למועד מועדים וחצי *Ki l’mo’ed mo’adim vachatzi*, in a time, the
time of the times and a half, וככלות נפץ יד עם קודש
*U’kechalot napetz yad am kodesh*, and when that time is done,
when the spreading forth of the holy nation, their power sort of
comes to an end, תכלינה כל אלה *Tichlena kol eleh*, then all
of this will come to an end. So meaning at a particular
set time and the people will be at a lowly state, then
this period of history will come to an end and Messianic period
will come. So that sounds like there's a fixed time and the
people aren't doing תשובה *Teshuvah* and so on. So it says, ושתק
רבי אליעזר *V’shatak Rabbi Eliezer*, and the end of that story is
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* had no answer. Like I don't know why
that was more sort of clear than other things, you know, but
nevertheless, it seems like רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* sort of conceded that
certainly the פסוקים *psukim* in דניאל *Daniel*... Look, the פסוקים *psukim* in
דניאל *Daniel* are the most explicit, are the most, you know, what's
it called,
eschatological of all the פסוקים *psukim* in the תורה Torah *Torah*, you
know, about describing a future time and whether it's the time of
the resurrection of the dead or the time of when the משיח
Mashiach *Mashiach*, although it doesn't use the phrase משיח Mashiach *Mashiach*, but
anyway will come and so on. So anyway, so that felt to
him like he was silent, he didn't have a good response to
that. ואמר רבי אבא *V’amar Rabbi Abba*, רבי אבא *Rabbi Abba* said,
אין לך קץ ketz מגולה מזה שנאמר shene'emar *Ein l’cha ketz meguleh
mizeh shene’emar*, you have no greater revealed end than this, as it
says. reveal end of time from this, like the
קץ ketz, הימים, that's a phrase קץ is referring to like when
is the משיח Mashiach coming? מחשבי קץ, Mechashvei ketz, we'll get to
those who compute the end of the days, שנאמר ואתם הרי ישראל
ענפכם תתנו ופריכם תשאו לעמי ישראל, sheneemar veatem harei yisrael anafchem titnu
ufriychem tisaou leami yisrael, you the mountains of Israel, your boughs will
blossom and your fruit you'll give for my nation Israel.
So now we
are going back to, you might remember we had something similar before,
shifting gears from this question about is it through תשובה or is
God going to force it, to the question about how will you
see whether it is the messianic period or not. And he is
saying you'll see it when it's a time of great prosperity. This
is the best סימן, siman, this is the best sign to know
you're in a messianic period, if it's a time of great prosperity.
Okay, רבי אלעזר אומר, Rebi Elazar omer, so now we're moving beyond
רבי אליעזר and רבי יהושע, this is רבי אלעזר, Rebi Elazar, not
רבי אליעזר. רבי אלעזר אומר, Rebi Elazar omer, אף מזה, af mizeh,
here's a better time, here's a better סימן, siman, שנאמר כי לפני
הימים ההם שכר אדם לא נהיה ושכר בהמה איננה, sheneemar ki lifnei
hayamim hahem sechar adam lo nihya usechar behema einena,
nobody would be able to hire out like people or animals. It's
the opposite. As opposed to a time of prosperity, it's a time
of great depression, of great scarcity, which is similar to an earlier
גמרא, Gemara, there was these different sort of issue visions of the
future time and the time that immediately precedes it. וליוצא ולבא אין
שלום מן הצר, Ulayotze velavo ein shalom min hatzar, there's no peace
for one who goes out and comes in from the oppression. מאי
וליוצא ולבא אין שלום מן הצר? Mai ulayotze velavo ein shalom min
hatzar? What does that mean? רב אבא אמר, Rav Abba amar, אף
תלמידי חכמים, af talmidei chachamim,
even Torah scholars that it's described in terms of peace, שנאמר שלום
רב לאוהבי תורתך, sheneemar shalom rav leohevei toratecha, אין שלום, ein shalom,
they will have no peace. They will not be able to sit
and learn תורה Torah. because they will have to be going out
and trying to earn a living, nobody will have any money and
so on. Okay.
Does that mean that they'll just be constantly bickering and arguing?
It could be that too.
רש״י Rashi says, no, רש״י Rashi doesn't say. מרוב הצרה, merov hatzara,
anyway fine, okay. מפני צר, mipnei tzar, from the צר. tzar. שכתוב
בהם שלום דכתיב אין
שלום מפני צר. shekatuv bahem shalom dechtiv ein shalom mipnei tzar.
So what's the צר? tzar? So רש״י Rashi says either the צר
tzar is the צרות tzarot because they'll also be afflicted by those,
by the difficult times, or from the יצר הרע yeitzer hara which
gets back to a sinful time, I guess. ושמואל אמר, Ushmuel amar,
עד שישוו כל השערים כולם שקולים, ad sheyishvu kol hashearim kulam shekulim,
until all of the prices are equal. So רש״י Rashi has two
versions whether this is going more like the first approach or the
second. Are they all equal that everything is equally cheap, wine costs
as little as flour? Or are they all equal that everything is
equally expensive, flour costs as much as wine?
So all right. אמר רבי חנינא, Amar Rebi Chanina, אין בן דוד
בא. ein Ben David ba. Now it's interesting the different languages of
קץ, and מחשבי הקץ, mechashvei haketz, the end of times, versus בן
דוד בא, Ben David ba, when will the Son of David come?
So again, I don't know exactly if they're describing different times or
if this was different genres in which they discuss this type of
an issue. But anyway, אין בן דוד בא עד שיתבקש דג לחולה
ולא ימצא. ein Ben David ba ad sheyitvakesh dag lechola velo yimatze.
It's going to be such a time of scarcity that even to
get a fish for a sick person you can't buy one. שנאמר
אז אשקיע מימיהם ונהרותם כשמן אוליכם. sheneemar az ashkiya meimeihem venaharotam kashemen
olichem.
Then I will sink down their waters and their rivers like oil
I will make it, I will make it flow. So like they
say, you can't get a fish, you won't be able to get
a fish out of the oil. It'll be like everything will be
stuck in there. וכתיב ביום ההוא אצמיח קרן לבית ישראל, Uchtiv bayom
hahu atzmiach keren leveit Yisrael, on
that day I will cause a blossoming of the horn of, the
pride of the children of Israel. אמר רבי חמא בר חנינא, Amar
Rebi Chama bar Chanina, אין בן דוד בא עד שתכלה מלכות הזלה
מישראל, ein Ben David ba ad shetichleh malchut hazala miYisrael, until even
until the lowly kingdom. Now what does it mean מלכות הזלה מישראל?
malchut hazala miYisrael? If you look at רש״י, Rashi, what does רש״י
Rashi say? שלא תהא להם שום שלטונות לישראל אפילו שלטונות קלה ודלה.
shelo tehe lahem shum
shiltonut leYisrael afilu shiltonut kala vedala.
So it doesn't mean that there won't be dominion over Israel, but
Israel won't even have the slightest, they will be totally subjugated to
the non-Jews. So this doesn't work in very much, right? It's sort
of like what חנינא Chanina is saying. Right. Are you trying to
work to get the generation to be כולו חייב? kulo chayav? Or
are you trying to work to get the generation to be כולו
זכאי? kulo zakai? So we're trying to sort of say the closer
we get to messianic periods is the
restoration of sovereignty in Israel and the more people are learning Torah
than they've ever learned before, and like we're doing all we can
to get it sort of closer to that vision of messianic times.
Or do you say no, this is actually the proof that it's
all מעשה שטן? maaseh satan? Because as long as we have some
sense of rule the משיח Mashiach is never going to come, we
have to be at the lowliest state and the most subjugated state.
שתכלה מלכות הזלה מישראל, Shetichleh malchut hazala miYisrael, שנאמר וכרת הזלזלים במזמרות,
sheneemar vecharat hazalzalim bemazmerot, cut off
the זלזלים zalzalim with a sheer, and here it's read like even
the slightest small type of sovereignty. וכתיב בתריה בעת ההיא יובל שי
להשם צבאות, Uchtiv batrei baet hahi yuval shai l'Hashem tzevaot, on that
day
presents will be given to God. It also might be a שי
shai and ישי Yishai type of a play on words there or
not. עם ממושך ומורט, Am memushach umorat,
a nation that is ממושך memushach and מורט, morat, which is like
a nation that is, that is... how do they translate it?
Lowly and torn. Pulled and torn. Okay. אמר רבי זירא אמר רבי
חנינא אין בן דוד בא עד שיכלו גסי הרוח מישראל, Amar Rabi
Zeira amar Rabi Chanina ein Ben David ba ad sheyichlu gasei haruach
miYisrael, until the haughty ones are no longer in Israel.
But before we had דור פני הכלב, dor pnei hakelev, right?
No, they're all conflictual, right? שנאמר כי אז אסיר מקרבך עליזי גאותך,
Shene'emar ki az asir mikirbecha alizei ga'avasecha, then I will remove from
your midst those who are like, you know, take haughty pride. וכתיב
והשארתי בקרבך עם עני ודל, Uchesiv vehisharti bekirbecha am ani vadal,
I will leave amongst you a lowly and poor nation, וחסו בשם
ה' vechasu beshem Hashem and they'll take refuge in God. Now here
though it's not necessarily poor in the financial sense, but poor in
the sense of humble, so maybe it's more talking about a righteous
period. So there's these two questions, right? Are we going to be
righteous or sinful and is the time going to be a prosperous
or a very difficult time, an afflicted time? אמר רב שמלאי משום
רבי אלעזר ברבי שמעון אין בן דוד בא עד שיכלו כל שופטים
ושוטרים מישראל, Amar Rav Simlai mishum Rabi Elazar berabi Shimon ein Ben
David ba ad sheyichlu kol shoftim veshotrim miYisrael, similar to the previous
idea, we'll lose all sense of all leadership, שנאמר ואשיבה ידי עליך
ואצרוף כבר סיגייך Shene'emar va'ashiva yadi alayich ve'etzrof kavar sigayich and then
ואשיבה שופטייך כבראשונה, ve'ashiva shoftayich kevarishona,
right,
exactly, I will sort of, you know, I will smelt out, you
know, your dross and then I will return your judges like the
past, so presumably means I'll get rid of all the current judges
which are all dross and I'll return the judges as they used
to be. Okay. אמר עולא אין ירושלים נפדית, Amar Ulla ein Yerushalayim
nifdis, some of the גרסא girsa אין ישראל נפדית, ein Yisrael nifdis,
אלא בצדקה, ela bitzedaka,
only in righteousness, שנאמר ציון במשפט תפדה ושביה בצדקה, Shene'emar Tzion bemishpat
tipadeh veshaveha bitzedaka,
Zion will be returned in justice and those who return to it
with righteousness or, you know, so again, not ברחמים, berachamim, you'll have
to earn it, which is why the Vilna Gaon in the ברכת
המזון Birkas Hamazon says בונה ירושלים אמן Boneh Yerushalayim Amen not בונה
ברחמיו ירושלים אמן Boneh berachamav Yerushalayim Amen כי אין ציון ki ein
Tzion because Zion is only redeemed בצדקה. bitzedaka. Right, I don't think
זה חסד zeh chesed also. Yeah,
a lot of these are exactly the תשעה באב Tisha B'av type
and the שבע דנחמתא Sheva d'Nechemta and whatever all these. אמר רב
פפא אי בטלו יהירי בטלו אמגושי, Amar Rav Papa ee batlu yeheiri
batlu amgushi, if the haughty ones were to cease then the Amgushi
were to cease, Amgushi is like Magi or it's also refers to
the, I think Amgushi doesn't actually means the non-Jews, it refers to
a specific type of the Babylonian like non-Jews who were caused obviously,
how do they translate it?
Here they say, it says sorcerers or fanatical idol worshippers.
Yeah, there you go, exactly those two. Right, Magi, it's sometimes translated
as Magi but also sometimes I think it's specifically certain like Zoroastrian
priests or whatever, I don't know, I didn't check it out.
But anyway, priestly class in ancient Persia.
Priestly class in ancient Persia. There you go.
What about אמגושי amgushi like the people who glean, what were those
called, like, you know, about when things are allowed for everybody to
take with נגושיא דפחא נגושיא? nigushia de'pacha nigushia?
Oh, no no, that's a different term, that's בזוזי דבזזי בזוזי buzuzei
d'vazzei buzuzei or something or yeah. Okay, anyway so Magi, Persian Magi.
Yeah,
I'm not sure, I think it was. Okay, anyway so
אי בטלו
יהירי בטלו אמגושי, ee batlu yeheiri batlu amgushi, okay, אי בטלו דייני
בטלו
גזירפטי, ee batlu dayani batlu gezirpati, which is also some like things
that are afflicting us.
Now we're going to show the evidence. אי בטלו יהירי בטלו אמגושי
דכתיב ואצרוף כבר סיגייך, ee batlu yeheiri batlu amgushi dechesiv ve'etzrof kavar
sigayich, I'll remove your dross, okay, which is, I don't know how
that's talking, how that's supposed to, we know that refers to the
haughty ones, but then
ואסירה כל בדילייך ve'asira kol bedilayich which Rashi says are those that
separate you from God, okay, so the Amgushi, the Magi, these
Zoroastrian priests, ואי בטלו דייני בטלו גזירפטי דכתיב הסיר ה' משפטייך, ve'ee
batlu dayani batlu gezirpati dechesiv hesir Hashem mishpatayich,
God has removed your judges, פנה אויבייך pina oyvayich and then your
enemies will be removed. So our judges are not doing us, so
clearly all this is a reference to, like, you know, leaders that
are arrogant leaders, haughty leaders, bad judges. אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabi
Yochanan and sort of blaming all of the problems that we have
from the non-Jews to our poor leadership which is an interesting connection,
right? And that's actually poor leadership is what's keeping us away from
God. אמר רבי יוחנן אם ראית דור שמתמעט והולך, Amar Rabi Yochanan
im ra'isa dor shemisma'et veholech,
if you're seeing a generation that things are getting, you know, getting
going from bad to worse, is shrinking and going down.
Oh, it doesn't mean like actual people are dying off?
Could be. I mean, again, it either means in terms of the,
you know, either the deeds are getting, like the righteousness is getting
worse or it means that the situation, the מצב matzav is getting
worse and worse.
חכה לו, chakei lo, you should still, still long for Mashiach, wait
for him. שנאמר ואת עם עני תושיע Shene'emar ve'es am ani toshia
and a poor people, right, God,
you know, He will redeem. So when things are getting bad, sort
of consistent with the previous point, that doesn't mean, you know, one
way is we're as far away as possible from the Messianic period
but the other vision is no, maybe it's דוקא davka when things
get... So terrible that God is going to come redeem us. So
it's also an important point just in terms of like don't give
up hope, you know, belief in the messianic period was so in
משיח Mashiach? was obviously what gave people hope when things were terrible,
right? So sort of just saying like you know it's interesting, I
mean I'd like to say it's not just like oh things are
terrible then God's going to have to save us and so, I
mean it fits into the debate of רבי אליעזר and רבי יהושע,
like is it going to come because we're going to make it
happen or is God just going to sort of force it to
happen? But also by having that idea that when things are really
terrible, you know, that could be a time when דווקא davka God
will bring משיח Mashiach. is something that helps give people hope at
bad times, which is a lot of how you know Jews lived
through you know their lives throughout Europe and whatever for hundreds of
years or thousands of years. So the idea that you know don't
worry, have patience, you know wait אף על פי שיתמהמה עם כל
זה אחכה לו af al pi sheyitmahmeha im kol ze achake lo
type of a thing, you know it could come at any time.
Yes, and it's interesting because you know I was actually in some
ways coming to the opposite conclusion that since no one's mentioned תשובה
that it just seems to like you know it's not even part
of the equation.
I know, that's what I was saying before, which is is that
the per- that don't get hung up on the statement that the
גמרא Gemara made that God earlier that oh you know the רבי
אליעזר approach the רבי יהושע approach God'll bring an evil king and
make them do תשובה. That's like one version of an idea that
you don't have to merit it yourself and bring it about yourself,
God is going to bring it. So that plays out in different
ways, okay? One way it plays out is God'll make them do
תשובה, but certainly here we're- it's absolutely correct, we're not seeing that
aspect of it, okay? Just like פרעה Paroh of
Egypt and the 49 levels of defilement, you know they were the
lowest level.
Right, there was the- right now then all the people will be
lost, right? Yeah, it's similar to that. You know I guess I'll
have to tell the you know there's a story that the rabbi
gets up on the you know on שבת Shabbat and he gives
a דרשה drasha and he says like you know we have to
be מצפה לביאת המשיח metzapeh l'viat haMashiach you know constantly we have
to be מחכה mechake any day משיח Mashiach could come, we have
to you know be longing for it, be מצפה metzapeh for it.
So the guy listens and he's like you know he's so inspired
and he goes home and he tells his wife and he says
you know the rabbi said that we have to be מצפה לביאת
המשיח metzapeh l'viat haMashiach and every day wait משיח Mashiach could come,
take us to ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, take us to ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
And the wife says like who wants משיח? Mashiach Like I have
it good here, you know we have a nice community, I've got
my nice friends, we've got a nice business going, like what- I
don't want you to pick up, move to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, move to
ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, we don't need משיח. Mashiach So the rabbi
goes back- so the guy goes back to the rabbi says you
know my wife says like what do we need משיח Mashiach for?
We have it good here, you know everything is good, you got
the chicken and the kids and whatever in our community, like why
do we need משיח Mashiach to come? So the rabbi says ah
he says but what about the פוגרומצ'יקס, pogromtchiks, you know they're you
know the גויים goyim who bring the פוגרום. pogrom. So he says-
so he goes back and he says to his wife so he
said so the rabbi said so but what about the פוגרומצ'יקס? pogromtchiks?
So the wife says go back and tell the rabbi משיח Mashiach
should come and bring the פוגרומצ'יקס pogromtchiks to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
Which
a lot of that could be said about the current American experience,
but anyway. But besides which it's like you're מצפה metzapeh for ביאת
המשיח biat haMashiach when things are bad, when you need to be
saved from your current reality, you know. So anyway, so he says
like this. All right.
אחכה לו, achake lo, wait for him, שנאמר ואת עם עני תושיע.
ve'et am ani toshia. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, אם ראית
דור שצרות רבות באות
עליו כנהר, im raita dor shetzarot rabot baot alav k'nahar, if you
see a generation where the afflictions, many afflictions are coming upon it
like a roaring- like a river, אחכה לו achake lo nevertheless, you
know wait for him. שנאמר כי יבוא כנהר צר shene'emar ki yavo
k'nahar tzar
when the affliction comes like a river, רוח השם נוססה בו ruach
Hashem nosesah bo
and the spirit of God is like- it's like doing destruction, is
like laying things to waste. וסמיך ליה ובא לציון גואל usamich lei
uva l'Tziyon goel
that's when a redeemer will come to Zion. אמר רבי יוחנן אין
בן דוד בא אלא בדור שכולו זכאי Amar Rabbi Yochanan ein ben
David ba ela b'dor shekulo zakai right, I mentioned this earlier, but
you know this is sort of playing into this, או כולו חייב,
o kulo chayav, or either all meritorious or all sinful. בדור שכולו
זכאי דכתיב ועמך כולם צדיקים לעולם ירשו ארץ B'dor shekulo zakai dechtiv
ve'amech kulam tzadikim l'olam yirshu aretz
okay, they will inherit the world when they are all righteous. בדור
שכולו חייב דכתיב וירא כי
אין איש B'dor shekulo chayav dechtiv vayar ki ein ish that there
was no man, וישתומם כי אין מפגיע vayishtomem ki ein mafgia and
was astounded that there was no intercessor, וכתיב למעני אעשה vechtiv l'ma'ani
e'eseh
I will do it says God for my sake. Okay, so this
is a sharper
sort of you know dichotomy than was mentioned earlier by רבי יהושע.
רבי יהושע spoke about God will bring something that will make them
do תשובה, so it was still going to be imposed by God,
it wasn't that the people brought about a better world, but at
the end you know at least you know this doesn't- isn't bringing
the תשובה into the- into the calculus at all. It's like either
they'll merit it or God's just going to bring it maybe דווקא
davka because as David was saying before if God doesn't bring it
now. Now right then as then then the whole thing is going
to all is going to be lost. Okay? And again, how does
that sort of presumably that's sort of somewhat in sync with the
idea of whether it's a prosperous time or a terrible financial time,
but anyway the גמרא Gemara doesn't exactly make the correspondence. Okay.
So now it says like this.
By the way though, that idea that either all is all meritorious
or all is about to be lost, right, and God's better bring
it now before before it all gets lost is different than the
idea of בעתה אחישנה, Be'itah Achishena, which we'll see—you didn't see that
yesterday, did you? I guess you did. Yeah, okay, thank you. Wait,
I keep on getting confused what's where in this גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
Anyway, let me just read it. Let me just read it. Okay.
Hold on, let me just read it. דכתיב... Dichshiv... okay... אמר רבי
אלכסנדרי רבי יהושע בן לוי רמי. Amar Rabbi Alexandri Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi rami. כתיב בעתה, Chtiv Be'itah, in its time I will bring
it, וכתיב אחישנה, u'chtiv Achishena, the very next word, in its time,
I will hasten it. So what is it? Will it come in
its time or will you hasten it? So זכו אחישנה. Zachu achishena.
If you merit, then I'll hasten it. לא זכו, Lo zachu, if
you don't merit, בעתה, be'itah, it'll come in its time. So that
idea that there's a fixed time, okay, is different than כולו חייב
או כולו זכאי. kulah chayav o kulah zakai. כולו חייב או כולו
זכאי Kulah chayav o kulah zakai still says like there's no fixed
time. Either, you know, it'll come because you've merited it and you've
made the world a perfect place or a more perfect place, or
because like it's better come now or everything is just going to—you're
going to—you know, it's you're all going—it's all going to be lost.
Okay, this is saying no. Like there is a fixed period in
which our current history will end or whatever, I don't know if
you think משיח Mashiach is a miraculous time, but anyway, in which
God is going to bring redemption, like he's got... and the thing
is that if we merit we can bring it sooner. I have
to tell you that there's something a little bit reassuring, but maybe
because it's reassuring it's also a little bit undermining of
human—disempowering from that vision, right? It's reassuring, which is like, oh okay,
eventually it's going to come. So even if we keep on messing
things up, there is a time when משיח Mashiach is going to
come. Okay, and that's better even than כולו חייב kulah chayav because
let's face it, nobody wants to say, 'Well, even if we don't
merit, we could always just make the world a horrific place and
then like,' you know, you don't want to sort of think of
the alternative there either. Okay, so sort of saying there's a fixed
time, it's like great, it's going to come eventually anyway. But, you
know, but it's also very disempowering. It's like, oh, so like it's
all part of God's plan and we can only like hasten it.
Like if we're really really good God will bring it sooner. Okay,
but it's like the fundamental orientation is a disempowering one. It's like,
okay, משיח's Mashiach going to come at a particular time. I can
even make it come sooner if you—if you know, if you're worthy.
Right, and that's I think very different than the idea which is
like it's our responsibility to bring this world closer to a messianic
period, it's our responsibility to, you know, to be זוכה zocheh and
to change the world and do תיקון עולם tikkun olam etc., you
know, to bring it closer—that fundamentally we bring about משיח Mashiach as
opposed to
fundamentally God is doing it but we can just hasten the timetable
a little bit. So I think it's really interesting sort of thinking
about what this does into that sense. On the one hand we
discussed the issue of hope, right, for bad times, but what it
also does in terms of a passive orientation towards the state of
the world or a very active ownership responsibility type of an orientation
to the state of the world. Yes, Michael.
So I was trying to understand though, because you know just having
read בראשית Bereishit and נח, Noach, with שחת הארץ לפניו... shicheit haaretz
lefanav... נח Noach is איש צדיק. ish tzadik. So you know, what's
the role of doing what we can? And like but the... you
know, the world isn't listening.
And like you know... yeah, I hear, right. Is שבור מלכא Shur
malka ישראל or all the... I don't know the answer to that.
It's a good... I... if I knew I would tell you, Michael.
Okay, so it says...
okay, where are we? זכו לא זכו בעתה. Zacho—lo zacho, be'itah. אמר
רבי אלכסנדרי רבי יהושע בן לוי רמי. Amar Rabbi Alexandri Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi rami. כתיב וארו עם ענני שמיא
כבר
אנש
אתה. Chtiv: Ve'aru im ananei shamaya kevar enosh ata. Like, you know,
there with the clouds of the heaven somebody like a man was
coming. וכתיב עני ורוכב על
החמור. U'chtiv: Ani verochev al hachamor. He'll be like a poor man
riding on a donkey. So is it going to be like a
glorious man like coming with honor and glory and coming in the
clouds of the heaven or going to be lowly and coming riding
on a donkey? So זכו עם ענני שמיא. zachu im ananei shamaya.
If they merit, then it comes with this glory. לא זכו Lo
zachu if they don't, עני ורוכב על החמור. ani verochev al hachamor.
Because obviously not just how משיח Mashiach is arriving but also sort
of reflecting the reality. Coming because you're so lowly, right, or coming
because you've achieved this great, you know, you've developed—you know, you have
brought the world to this state. Okay.
אמר ליה שבור מלכא לשמואל. Amar lei Shur malka l'Shmuel. שבור מלכא
Shur malka was the Persian king, said to שמואל: אמריתו משיח על
חמרא אתי. Amritu Mashiach al chamara ati. I hear you guys saying
that משיח Mashiach comes on a donkey.
So you know, אישדר ליה סוסיא, ishel lei susaya, you know what,
I'll send him one of my horses. Why does he need a
donkey? I'll send him a Cadillac, okay, ברקא, Baraka, like a fast
horse דאית ליה. de-is lih. אמר ליה, amre lih, מי אית לך
בר חיור גווני? mi is lach bar chivor gavnei? Ah, but do
you have but do you have one that's a hundred different colors?
So Rashi says I like I don't know like he was he
was just sort of like, you know, just giving him some nonsense
answer. It's not any donkey Moshiach is going to come on. He's
going to come on a super donkey. Anyway, רבי יהושע בן לוי
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi אשכח לאליהו. ashkach l'Eliyahu. He saw Eliyahu דהוה
קאי אפיתחא דמערתא de-hava ka'i a-pitcha de-ma'arta of רבי שמעון בן יוחאי.
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai.
He was there by the opening of the cave of Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai. Now what the significance of Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai is
here is unclear, but anyway, אמר ליה, amre lih, he said to
him: אתינא לעלמא דאתי? atina l'alma de-asei? Bring me to the world
to come. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, אתינא לעלמא דאתי? atina l'alma de-asei?
I'm sorry, who sees a question? Yeah, אתינא, asina,
when will you be bringing—how do they read the grammar—will I, oh
all right, אתינא, atina, right, I'm sorry, I'm jumping ahead to later.
אתינא לעלמא דאתי? atina l'alma de-asei? Will I enter into the world
to come? אמר ליה, amre lih, אם ירצה אדון זה, im yirtzeh
adon zeh, if God desires. Oh, okay.
אדון זה, adon zeh, does it mean like Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai?
I also thought that at first, but that's not how Rashi explains,
like why should Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai determine if you're coming into
the world to come? Anyway, if God desires.
Must be the fact that he was on the מערה me'arah
means—yeah, I know, like Rashi doesn't give any significance to that, just
makes it a historical detail. We can discuss if there's significance, let's
keep on reading. אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi, שנים ראיתי וקול ג' שמעתי. shnayim ra'iti ve-kol gimel shamati. I
only saw two people there, me and Eliyahu, but I heard a
third voice which apparently Rashi says was the שכינה. Shechinah. Again, from
the context just thinking it's Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. Anyway, let's keep
on reading. אמר ליה, amre lih, I said to him: אימת אתי
משיח? eimas asi Moshiach? Okay,
so when is Moshiach going to come? אמר
ליה, amre lih: he said to him or he said back to
me: זיל שייליה לדידיה. zil shaylei l'didei. Why ask me? Go ask
Moshiach. Okay, I mean Eliyahu is the
harbinger of Moshiach, but go ask Moshiach himself when he's going to
come. והיכא יתיב? ve-heicha yasiv? So where is he sitting that I
can go ask him? So he said: אפיתחא דקרתא. a-pitcha de-karta. Now
our version is on the opening of the city, but the actual
גרסא girsa is on the opening of Rome, the gates of Rome.
Okay. ומאי סימניה? u-mai simanei? How will I notice which one is
him? So יתיב ביני עניי סובלי חלאים. yasiv beinei aniyei sovlei cholayim.
He's sitting there amongst all the poor
that are ill and that have these wounds and whatever, you know,
these pus coming out of them and so on. We'll see. וכולן
שרו ואסירי. ve-kulan sharu ve-asiri. They're all undoing their bandages and then
redoing their bandages בחד זימנא. be-chad zimna. Oh, I'm sorry. וכולן שרו
בחד זימנא, ve-kulan sharu be-chad zimna, that
they take off all their bandages, they dress their wounds, and they
re-bandage themselves. איהו שרי חד ואסיר חד. ihu shari chad ve-asir chad.
He is taking off one bandage, dressing it, and then putting it
back on one at a time. אמר, amar, why? He says: דילמא
מבעינא, dilma mive'ina,
maybe I'll be needed דלא איעכב, de-lo i'akev, maybe the time will
come any second and
I'll have to come immediately, so I don't want to have all
my bandages off at that time, so I have to be any
second ready to go. Okay. אזל לגביה. azal l'gabeih. So he went
to him by Rome and he found Moshiach. אמר ליה, amre lih,
he says: שלום עליך רבי ומורי, shalom alecha rabbi u-mori, peace to
you my Rebbe and my master. אמר ליה: amre lih, שלום עליך
בר ליואי, shalom alecha bar livai, peace to you Bar Livai, which
was Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. אמר ליה, amre lih: לאימת אתי מר?
l'eimas asi mar? So I'm sorry,
אמר
ליה, amre lih: he said to him: When will the master come?
אמר ליה: amre lih: היום, hayom, today. Okay. אתא לגבי
אליהו, asa l'gabei Eliyahu, he came back to Eliyahu. אמר ליה: amre
lih: מאי אמר לך? mai amar lach? So Eliyahu said: What did
Moshiach tell you? אמר ליה: amre lih, שלום עליך בר ליואי. shalom
alecha bar livai. He said to me peace to you Bar Livai.
אמר ליה: amre lih: אבטחא לך ולבוך לעלמא דאתי. aftacha lach u-lavuch
l'alma de-asei.
So you were asking if you'll come to the world to come,
by the fact that he greeted you and he said Shalom Alecha
and he called you Bar Livai, he called you by your father's
name, that is a סימן siman that both you and your father
are going to enter into עולם הבא. Olam Ha-ba. Okay, so that
was the answer to your question. Now אמר ליה, so then he
said to Eliyahu, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi: שקורי קשקר בי, shakorei kashkar
bi, he lied to me. דאמר לי היום אתינא. de-amar li hayom
atina. He said he's coming today ולא אתא, ve-lo asa, didn't come.
I guess it took more than a day to get back from
Rome to the cave of Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai. Okay, ולא
אתא, ve-lo asa, didn't come. אמר ליה: הכי אמר לך. hachi amar
lach. No, no, no, here's what he was saying to you: היום
אם בקולו תשמעו. hayom im bekolo tishmau.
He can come today—he'll come today if only you listen to God's
voice. I love this מדרש, midrash, it's so great. He's coming today,
yeah, היום אם בקולו תשמעו. hayom im bekolo tishmau. Any day Moshiach
could come—every day is today if you merit it. Now the idea
of him being at Rome and being sick and whatever, you know,
clearly it seems to evoke this idea first of all that Rome
is what do you call it, you know, that Rome represents like,
you know, the sovereignty over the Jewish people, they're under Christianity, like
all the forces that are, you know, that are preventing like the
evil forces that are preventing Moshiach from coming.
And so certainly there's this set and that, you know, and he's
there afflicted etc. So certainly he's like representing the Jewish people, right,
that are there under the oppression and the affliction of Rome etc.
and that, you know, and that, you know, but somehow through that
and through that oppression... ultimately will emerge, you know, the Messianic times
and it could be instantaneous. You could go from being this afflicted
nation, which is binding and unbinding their bandages, but you know, don't
spend too much time, it's almost saying, this is the way I
would read it. Like seeing משיח Mashiach as a sort of a
distillation, what's the word? Apotheosis? Anyway, whatever, of the Jewish people, right?
So there you are, you're under Rome, you're in Rome, you know,
but you're at the gates of Rome, you're not fully in, you're
not Rome, you know, Jewish is sort of at the boundary point,
but you're sort of influenced by it. You're under their sovereignty. And
like, don't spend too much all of your time worrying about your
wounds, you know, sort of, you know, you know, take care as
you have to, but always be expecting any moment משיח Mashiach could
come, you know, sort of always be looking at that possibility rather
than that, you know, if you're spending an hour undoing, redoing your
wounds or whatever, that's your whole focus is on your suffering. You
know, obviously you have to address your wounds, but it should always
be with a look that at any time like משיח Mashiach can
come and that's היום אם בקולו תשמעו. Hayom im bekolo tishma'u. So
I see sort of thinking about that and that sort of representing
this Jewish state and about the idea of even when things are
bad, חכה לו, Chakeh lo, right, sort of works very well together.
The רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai aspect is interesting
because רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai ran to the
cave, right, where the... remember why רבי שמעון בר יוחאי Rabbi Shimon
bar Yochai ran to the cave?
It was the first... I mean he was being sought out by
the Romans.
By the Romans. Right, so it was sort of like, you know,
running away, you know, from that sort of Roman presence. I wonder
again how much of a whole Rome thing, making sure that you're
able to do מצוות, mitzvot, you know, sort of I don't know
exactly how that all fits in. I did want to mention that
this issue about this אגדתא, Agadata, if people are curious, you know,
I mentioned at the beginning of חלק Chelek that רמב"ן Ramban has
a שער הגמול Sha'ar HaGemul where he collects all of the different
מדרשים, Midrashim, most of them from חלק, Chelek, but anyway other places
as well, about עולם הבא, Olam HaBa, תחיית המתים, Techiyat HaMeitim, שכר
ועונש Sechar VaOnesh and tries to sort of arrange it all, you
know. And we discussed some of those things at the opening. He
also has in the כתבי הרמב"ן Kitvei HaRamban is the record of
his debate, of his disputation. You've all heard the disputation of Barcelona,
right, with this guy, with this apostate, פראיי פאול? Frai Paul? What
was it? פאול Paul something? Anyway, so one of the things that
factor into it is our אגדתא, Agadata, is our גמרא Gemara right
here, I mean a lot of the אגדתות. Agadot. But let me
just sort of read you one line. Oh-oh, I hope I brought
the right one. Yikes.
That's okay, you have the whole thing here.
Here. No, okay. He says, okay, חזר אותו האיש ואמר כי בתלמוד
מפורש שרבי יהושע בן לוי שאל לאליהו מתי יבא משיח והשיבו שאל
למשיח עצמו היכן הוא בפתח דרומא בין החולים.
Chazar oto ha'ish ve'amar ki baTalmud meforash sheRabbi Yehoshua ben Levi sha'al
le'Eliyahu matai yavo Mashiach veheshivo
she'al laMashiach atzmo heichan hu befetach deRoma bein hacholim.
Nice Hebrew translation of our גמרא. Gemara. שאל לו ואם כן כבר
בא והוא ברומא והוא ישו המושא ברומא. She'alo ve'im ken kevar ba
vehu beRoma vehu Yeshu hamosha beRoma. Oh, you see,
he already came and he's in Rome and that's Jesus cause now
Rome is a Christian, you know, it's Christian, the Holy Roman Empire,
etc. So you see he already came. עניתי לו הלא מפורש מכאן
שלא בא שהרי שאלו לאליהו מתי יבא. Aniti lo halo meforash mikan
shelo ba sheharei sha'alo le'Eliyahu matai yavo.
He's alive, but he didn't come yet! וכן שאלו למשיח עצמו מתי
אתי מר אם כן לא בא עדיין. Vechein sha'alo laMashiach atzmo matai
ati mar im ken lo ba adayin. But although, as far as
פשוטו של אגדתא הללו, pshuto shel Agadata halalu, it sounds like he
was born, because then the problem is he was already born then.
How old is he? He's a thousand years old by the time
רמב"ן Ramban was talking. So רמב"ן Ramban says what's the big deal,
you know, מתושלח Metushelach lived a thousand years. Anyway, but then he
says, ואיני מאמין בכך, ve'eini ma'amin bekach, but I don't believe this
אגדתא Agadata anyway. Okay? And then they go on back and forth,
and then he says, you know, he says what do you mean
you don't believe this? So he says, and then so then it
says like after they disputed in front of the king, they had
a whole presentation in front of like all the people, I think
Jews and Christians together. And he said like this, קמתי ואמרתי שמעו
עמים כולם פראיי פאול אמר שכבר בא משיח שדברו בו הנביאים ואמרתי
שלא בא והביא ספר אגדתא שאמר בו שביום שחרב בית המקדש בו
ביום נולד ואמרתי אני שאיני מאמין בזה. Kamti ve'amarti shim'u amim kulam
Frai Paul amar shekevar ba Mashiach shedibru vo hanevi'im ve'amarti shelo ba
vehevi sefer Agadata she'amar bo shebeyom shecharav Beit HaMikdash bo bayom nolad
ve'amarti ani she'eini ma'amin bezeh.
I don't believe in this אגדתא. Agadata. I don't believe it's literal.
אלא ראיה לדברי, Ela re'aya lidevarai, but if you do believe in
it, it's a proof to me. You know, because Jesus wasn't born
after the temple was destroyed, right? So ועתה אני אפרש לכם למה
אמרתי שאיני מאמין בזה אצלנו יש לנו שלשה מינים של ספרים.
ve'ata ani afareish lachem lama amarti she'eini ma'amin bezeh
etzlenu yesh lanu shlosha minim shel sefarim.
We have two types of literature, three types. האחד הוא הביבליה וכולנו
מאמינים בו אמונה שלמה, He'echad hu haBiblia vekhulanu ma'aminim bo emunah shleimah,
cause he's talking to Christians. Okay, we have the Bible. השני הוא
נקרא תלמוד והוא פירוש למצות התורה. Hasheni hu nikra Talmud vehu peirush
lemitzvot haTorah. That's a commentary to the מצוות mitzvot of the תורה.
כי בתורה יש תרי"ג מצות ואין בה אחת שלא נתפרשה בתלמוד, Ki
baTorah yesh taryag mitzvot ve'ein bah achat shelo nitparshah baTalmud,
so it's our commentary to the Bible.
ואנחנו מאמינים בו בפירוש המצות. Ve'anachnu ma'aminim bo bepeirush hamitzvot. ויש
לנו ספר שלישי הנקרא מדרש.
Veyesh lanu sefer shlishi hanikra
Midrash.
רוצה לומר, Rotzeh lomar, sermons.
כמו
שאם יעמוד ההגמון Kemo
she'im ya'amod haAgmon
and he gave a sermon and one of the listeners liked it
and wrote it down. Somebody got
up, gave a sermon, somebody liked it. If you don't want to
believe in it, no problem. ויש חכמים שכתבו שהמשיח לא יולד עד
קץ העולם *veyeish chachamim shekatvu shehamashiach lo yeivaled ad keitz ha'olam* and
it goes through and it basically says, look, these are all just
מדרשים *Midrashim*. You can believe them, you can not believe them, I
don't believe in them, so they're not a proof, they're not a
proof to you when משיח Mashiach? *Mashiach* when, you know, if Jesus
is the Messiah. But even if you do believe in it, he
says, you know, the simple logic and the chronology of it doesn't
match up. Just because it happened, you know, roughly at the time
of the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash* and it has Rome, doesn't all
of a sudden become a proof to your claim. Anyway, it's very
interesting if you want to see, you know, in the ויכוח הרמב"ן
*Vikuach HaRamban*, it's actually been translated into English about how a lot
of our גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort of factor in. Yeah, Michael.
Yeah, but what's interesting about the point you made is that, you
know,
sometimes I think there's a misconception that, you know, משיח Mashiach. *Mashiach*
means he's born into the ראשית *reshit*, some people say משיח Mashiach
בן יוסף *Mashiach ben Yosef*, משיח Mashiach בן דוד *Mashiach ben David*.
It's like, you know, I don't know how any of
that—I don't know at all if it's either. Okay. Moving on. So,
היום אם בקולו תשמעו *Hayom im bekolo tishmau*. שאלו תלמידיו את רבי
יוסי בן קיסמא *Sha'alu talmidav et Rabbi Yosi ben Kisma*, אימתי בן
דוד בא *Eimatai ben David ba*? When is בן דוד *ben David*
going to come? אמר מתיירא אני שמא תבקשו ממני אות *Amar mityarei
ani shema tevakeshu mimeni ot*. I don't want to tell you because
then you're going to ask me to give you a sign that
it's the truth. אמרו לו אין אנו מבקשים ממך אות *Amru lo
ein anu mevakshim mimcha ot*. No, no, no, we're not going to
ask you for a sign. אמר להם לכשיפול השער הזה ויבנה ויפול
ויבנה ויפול ואין מספיקין לבנותו עד שבן דוד בא *Amar lahem lechesyipol
hasha'ar hazeh veyibaneh veyipol veyibaneh veyipol ve'ein maspikin livnoto ad sheben David
ba*. When this gate falls, the gate of Rome, ויבנה ויפול ויבנה
ויפול *veyibaneh veyipol veyibaneh veyipol* fall again and be rebuilt, and I'm
sorry, when לכשיפול השער הזה ויבנה ויפול ויבנה ויפול ואין מספיקין לבנותו
עד שבן דוד בא *lechesyipol hasha'ar hazeh veyibaneh veyipol veyibaneh veyipol ve'ein
maspikin livnoto ad sheben David ba*.
It'll fall and be rebuilt twice and then the third time it'll
fall and then בן דוד *ben David* will come. So presumably he
means not just the physical gate, he means like Rome will collapse
and then there'll be a—something will come in its place and collapse
and then the third time. Anyway, אמרו לו רבינו תן לנו אות
*Amru lo Rabbeinu ten lanu ot*. Give us a sign. אמר להם
ולא כך אמרתם לי שאין אתם מבקשים ממני אות *Amar lahem velo
kach amartem li she'ein atem mevakshim mimeni ot*? You promised you weren't
going to ask for a sign. אמרו לו ואף על פי כן
*Amru lo ve'af al pi chen*. Okay, we promised, but still, give
us a sign. אמר להם אם כך יהפכו מי מערת פמיאס לדם
*Amar lahem im kach yehafechu mei me'arat Pamyas ledam*, which is all
so evocative, right, about the whole period of Moshe and whatever, let
the waters of פמיאס *Pamyas*, which feeds, I think, to the Jordan,
let them turn into blood. ונהפכו לדם *Venehefechu ledam*. Okay. I don't
know what to make of that.
Wait, he wanted an אות *ot* of what, that
what he said is true? That what he said is true, that
that's going to be the sign that משיח *Mashiach* is going to
come. Okay, בשעת פטירתו אמר להם המיקו לי ארוני *Besha'at petirato amar
lahem hamiku li aroni*. Put my—pit my casket deep into the earth.
שאין כל דקל ודקל שבבבל שאין סוס של פרסיים נקשר בו *She'ein
kol dekel vedekel shebeBavel she'ein sus shel Parsiyim nikshar bo*. Because the
Messianic period is going to be one of great war, and every
single—they're gonna come from בבל *Bavel*, the armies of גוג ומגוג Gog
u'Magog, *Gog uMagog*, and every single palm tree will have a horse
tied to it, so that's just how big the troops will be.
ואין כל ארון וארון שבארץ ישראל שאין סוס מדי אוכל בו תבן
*Ve'ein kol aron ve'aron shebe'eretz Yisrael she'ein sus Madai ochel bo teven*.
And then when they come into Israel and the war of גוג
ומגוג *Gog uMagog*, and they will dig out all of the coffins
and use the coffins for feeding troughs for their horses. So I
want my coffin to be very deeply buried so I shouldn't have
to experience, you know, even my body, the all this anguish at
the time leading up to משיח *Mashiach*. So now we're also a
little bit trans—gonna transition from משיח *Mashiach* to the חבלי משיח *chevlei
Mashiach*, the birth pangs of משיח *Mashiach*, and the war of גוג
ומגוג *Gog uMagog* that's going to precede it. Okay. שאין סוס מדי
אוכל בו תבן *She'ein sus Madai ochel bo teven*. אמר רב אין
בן דוד בא עד שתפשוט המלכות הרשעה על ישראל תשעה חודשים *Amar
Rav ein ben David ba ad shetifshot hamalchut haresha'ah al Yisrael tishah
chodashim*. Until the government, meaning the Romans or whatever, you know, will
have dominion over Israel for nine months. Now you'll say what do
you mean, that's been much more than nine months? So many have
the גרסא *girsa* not ישראל *Yisrael* but על כל העולם כולו *al
kol ha'olam kulo*. Okay, on the entire world. Okay, so meaning that
whatever the, you know, the Romans or whatever, the evil government is,
they have dominion over the entire world for nine months. Like רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says,
no the רש"י Rashi *Rashi* doesn't say anything about that. Okay, על
בני ישראל *al benei Yisrael*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says היינו כל העולם
שישראל מפוזרים בו *hainu kol ha'olam sheYisrael mefuzarim bo*. So רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* actually—some have the גרסא *girsa* the whole world, some even with
the גרסא *girsa* על ישראל *al Yisrael* it means wherever there are
Jewish people, they are under the dominion of this one foreign government.
Now the nine months is of course evocative of birth pangs, right?
Because משיח *Mashiach* is going to be birthed, and in the birthing
there's a lot of anguish before the baby is born, there's the
birth pangs. Okay, so nine months. שנאמר לכן יתנם עד עת יולדה
ילדה *Shene'emar lachein yitnem ad eit yoledah yaladah*, until they will give
them until the time of the—that the childbirth will be—will be birthed,
ויתר אחיו ישובון על בני ישראל *veyeter achav yeshuvun al benei Yisrael*.
And the remnant of the—of the brethren will turn to בני ישראל
*benei Yisrael*. So this actually fits with רש"י'ס *Rashi's* read of על
ישראל *al Yisrael*, the remnant of the brethren, where all Israel is
scattered, for those—only then after these nine months of pregnancy and birth,
so then everybody will return.
אמר עולא ייתי
ולא איחמיניה *Amar Ulla yeitei velo eichminei*. Let משיח *Mashiach* come, but
let me not see it. Let it not happen in my days.
I don't want to have to suffer through the period of the
חבלי משיח *chevlei Mashiach*, this period of the suffering that precedes it.
So it's so funny, you should be מחכה לו *mechakeh lo* but
like hope for it to come, but I want it to come
right after I die. Okay, I shouldn't have to suffer through וכן
אמר רבא *Vechein amar Rava* or Rabba says ייתי ולא אחמיניה *yeisei
velo echaminei*. Let it come but let me not see it. יוסף
אמר *Yosef amar* ייתי ואיזכי *yeisei ve'ezkeh*. Let it come and I
should only merit דאיתיב בטולא דכופיתא דחמרא *da'eisiv betulla dechufisa dechamra* that
I should sit in the shade of the dung of משיח *Mashiach*
donkey. Meaning that I don't care how much I have to suffer,
I want to be alive at that time. If he comes from
heaven there will be no donkey. Well, that's true. Anyway, אמר ליה
אביי לרבא *Amar lei Abaye leRava*, Abaye says to Rava, מאי טעמא
*mai ta'ama*, why do you not want to experience see משיח *Mashiach*
come? By the way, this very also parallels with the גמרא *Gemara*
in the beginning of ברכות *Berachot*, which is יסורין של אהבה *yissurin
shel ahavah*, that certain Rabbis said, you know, if you're suffering and
you don't understand why, you're totally righteous, it's God is bringing you
יסורין של אהבה *yissurin shel ahavah*. So some Rabbi, you know, very
right after that גמרא *Gemara* other Rabbis were suffering and they said
חביבין עליך יסורין *chavivin alecha yissurin*, do you value the יסורין *yissurin*
because it's a sign of God's love and it's a way that
God can give you even more reward? And they, so many of
them there said לא הן ולא שכרן *lo hein velo secharan*, I'd
rather do without them and without their reward. Right, so it's certainly
a parallel here. Okay, so Abaye said to Rava מאי טעמא *mai
ta'ama*, why do you not want משיח *Mashiach* to come in your
day? אילימא משום חבלי של משיח *eileima mishum chevlei shel Mashiach*, the
birth pangs of משיח *Mashiach*, right? והתניא *vehatanya*, right,
you know that's by the what we do in שבת זמירות *Shabas
zmiros* right מחבלי משיח *mechevlei Mashiach*, מחבלי *mechevlei*, you know, okay, so
anyway, והתניא *vehatanya*, it's taught in a ברייתא *Baraita* שאלו תלמידיו את
רבי אליעזר מה יעשה אדם וינצל מחבלי של משיח *sha'alu talmidav es
Rabbi Eliezer mah ya'aseh adam veyinatzel mechevlei shel Mashiach*? There's a way
to be protected from the birth pangs of משיח *Mashiach*. They asked
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* what to do and he said יעסוק בתורה
ובגמילות חסדים *ya'asok baTorah uvigmilus chasadim*, just learn תורה *Torah* and do
acts of righteousness, and then maybe even if it happens in your
day, you at least will be safe. ומר הא תורה והא גמילות
חסדים *u'mar ha Torah veha gmilus chasadim*, you both have תורה *Torah*
and acts of kindness. אמר ליה *Amar lei*, he said to him,
שמא יגרום החטא *shema yigrom hacheit*. No, I'm still afraid that
maybe I will sin and I will not be perfect and in
perfect state, you know, and whatever, and because of some sins that
I have, I will be exposed to the suffering of משיח *Mashiach*
or to the birth pangs of משיח *Mashiach*. כדרבי יעקב בר אידי
דאמר d'amar, רבי יעקב בר אידי *kedirabbi Yaakov bar Idi de'amar rabbi
Yaakov bar Idi*, רמי כתיב *rami kesiv*, he showed a contradiction. It
says הנה אנכי עמך ושמרתיך בכל אשר תלך *hinei anochi imcha ushmarticha
bechol asher telech*, God promised יעקב *Yaakov* I'll be with you wherever
you go.
And it's written ויירא יעקב מאד וייצר לו *vayira Yaakov me'od vayetzer
lo*, that when he returned he was afraid. What was he afraid
of? God promised that He'll be with him. מסיטפי שמא יגרום החטא
*mistafei shema yigrom hacheit*, he was afraid that or שמא גרם החטא
*shema garama hacheit*. Anyway, he was afraid that because maybe he had
sinned he no longer merits. So even with God's divine protection and
promise of the divine protection, the promise is only as good as
long as you continue to merit it. Okay, so that's with God's
promise. So he says even though I have תורה *Torah* and מצוות
*mitzvos* I can't presume and גמילות חסדים *gmilus chasadim* that I won't
have some sin that will expose me to the sufferings of משיח
*Mashiach*. כדתניא *kedetanya*, as it's taught, עד יעבור עמך ה' *ad ya'avor
amcha Hashem*, this is from the שירה *shira*, זו ביאה ראשונה *zu
biah rishonah*, this is the first entrance into ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*.
עד יעבור עם זו קנית *ad ya'avor am zu kanisa*, the nation
you acquired, זו ביאה שניה *zu biah shniyah*. אמור מעתה *Emor mei'ata*,
say from now, ראויים היו ישראל לעשות להם נס בביאה שניה *re'uyim
hayu Yisrael la'asot lahem neis biviah shniyah*. What was the second entrance?
When they came in the time of בית שני *Bayit Sheini*. So
in בית שני *Bayit Sheini* it should have been as miraculous as
a time to be ביאה ראשונה *biah rishonah* like בית ראשון *Bayit
Rishon*. It should have been like with war and self-sovereignty,
right, as opposed to when they came and in בית שני *Bayit
Sheini* it was under the permission of the, you know, of the
Persian government, right, but it wasn't that they were sovereign and it
wasn't with miracles. אלא שגרם החטא *ella shegaram hacheit*, even though it
had been implicitly promised, because of the sin it did not happen.
Okay, so therefore the point is that even when there are these
promises you have to continue to merit it. וכן אמר רבי יוחנן
amar Rabbi Yochanan, *Vechein amar Rabbi Yochanan*, back to this point, Rabbi
Yochanan said ייתי ולא אחמיניה *yeisei velo echaminei*, let it come and
let me not see it. אמר ליה ריש לקיש *Amar lei Reish
Lakish*, Reish Lakish said to him, מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*, why? אילימא
משום דכתיב *eileima mishum dechesiv* כאשר ינוס איש מפני הארי ופגשו הדוב
*ka'asher yanus ish mipnei ha'ari ufegasho hadov*, it'll be at that time
like a person will run away from the lion and then the
bear will encounter him, ובא הבית וסמך ידו על הקיר ונשכו נחש
*uva habayit vesamach yado al hakir unishacho nachash*, he'll run to the
house, he'll put his hand on the wall and then a snake
will bite him, meaning you'll be running from one trouble to the
next trouble. Okay, so that's why you're afraid? Nah, that can be
fulfilled in much softer ways. בא וראה דוגמתו בעולם הזה *Bo ure'ei
dugmaso ba'olam hazeh*, come and see its example in this world. So
even nowadays that we have something that is the fulfillment of that
verse. בזמן שאדם יוצא לשדה *Bizman she'adam yotzei lasadeh*, you're going out
to the field, ופגע בו סנטר *ufaga bo santeir*, a סנטר *santeir*
is like a chin, right, isn't that in modern Hebrew? Or a
jaw? I think a jaw. Anyway, but here it means רש"י Rashi,
*Rashi* says it's the person who basically determines, you know, your field
and does a property assessment and determines like, you know, where the
boundaries of the field are. So you're running into the field, you
go to the field and you meet some government official who's then
levying taxes on you or changing the boundaries of your field. דומה
כמי שפגעו ארי *domeh kemi shepaga'o ari*, it's like you encountered a
lion. נכנס לעיר *nichnas la'ir*, then you come back to the city,
ופגע בו גבאי *ufaga bo gabbai*, and then the tax collector starts,
you know, asks you for your back taxes, דומה כמי שפגעו דוב
*domeh kemi shepaga'o dov*, it's like a bear now encountered you. נכנס
לביתו *nichnas leveiso*, you go to your house, ומצא בניו ובנותיו מוטלים
ברעב *umatza banav uvnotav mutalim bera'av*, and the kids, everybody's hungry and
starving, דומה כמי שנשכו נחש *domeh kemi shenishacho nachash*. So, you know,
don't have to take these verses as literal. Don't be so afraid
of the period of משיח. It doesn't mean it's all literally going
to happen like this.
Any type of affliction, afflictions we have even nowadays. אלא משום דכתיב,
ela mishum d'chtiv, but because the verse says, שאלו נא וראו אם
ילד זכר, sha'alu na u're'u im yalad zachar, go and ask if
a male has ever given birth, מדוע ראיתי כל גבר ידיו על
חלציו, madua raiti kol gever yadav al chalatzav, why have I seen
all men with their hands on their sides כיולדה, k'yoleda, like a
woman giving birth, ונהפכו כל פנים לירקון, v'nehefchu kol panim l'yerakon,
and all faces have turned to like yellow to jaundice, which refers
to a time of real tremendous affliction. Also by metaphor, מה ראיתי
כל גבר, ma raiti kol gever, אמר רב יצחק אמר רב, amar
Rav Yitzchak amar Rav, מי שכל גבורה שלו, mi shekol g'vura shelo,
the one who all the power is to him, meaning God, God
is in pain the same way that these periods of משיח are
where we're suffering and we're in birth pains, God is also suffering
these birth pains of משיח as well. God is in suffering as
well. ומאי ונהפכו כל פנים לירקון? u'mai v'nehefchu kol panim l'yerakon? אמר
רבי יוחנן, פמליא של מעלה ופמליא של מטה, pamalia shel ma'ala u'pamalia
shel mata,
both the heavenly hosts above and below, up there in heaven and
down here, everybody is suffering during this time. בשעה שאמר הקדוש ברוך
הוא, besha'a she'amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, הללו מעשה ידי והללו מעשה ידי,
halalu ma'aseh yadai v'halalu ma'aseh yadai, and not only that, why is
everybody in anguish? Because
at the time of גוג ומגוג, ultimately it's when Israel's going to
win over the non-Jews and there's going to be this tremendous war,
but God is going to be suffering because it's going to mean
the deaths of people whether they're Jews or not. These are my
creatures and those are my creatures. It's going to be a time
of great suffering even if we the Jewish people emerge victorious. That
doesn't change the idea that from God's perspective, the world's perspective, it's
going to be a time of great suffering. היכא דאלי מיני אלי,
hecha d'alei minei alei, how can I wipe out these for the
sake of those? ואמר רב פפא, v'amar Rav Pappa, היינו דאמרי אינשי,
hainu d'amri inshi, that's why people say, that's like people say, רציא
ונפל תורא, ratzya v'nafal tora, if your ox was going and fell
down, ואזלו ושדיו לסוסיא באורייא, v'azlu v'shadyu l'susa b'urya,
and you then you put a horse in its place by the
feeding trough. Meaning, so the way רש"י Rashi? explains it is is
like okay, you wanted your cow and now instead you had to
put the horse there, but now you got to like your horse.
So now to have to replace your horse back with the original
cow is going to be a pain for you as well. God
replaced
the success of the Jews, the Jews as it were with the
non-Jews have sovereignty, they're now sort of favored. So even though originally
God still has his love for us or whatever, it's hard for
God now he has to reverse things and replace now the non-Jews
with the Jews and so on. It's an interesting image. Anyway, the
point being it's going to be a time of great suffering for
the world and not only for the world but for God as
well and so on.
Okay, so let's just read I guess one more sentence. אמר רב
גידל אמר רב, amar Rav Gidel amar Rav, עתידין ישראל דאכלי שני
משיח, atidin Yisrael d'achli shne Mashiach, the Israel will benefit and the
Messianic times, they're the ones that will sort of be the ones
that'll be prosperous. אמר רב יוסף, amar Rav Yosef, פשיטא, pshita, obviously.
אלא מאן אכיל להו, ela man achil lehu, who who do you
think is going to be prosperous during the time? Lou? חיוי ובילי?
Chivi u'Vili? Now רש"י says it says חיוי ובילי Chivi u'Vili means
anything, just mean like nonsense names. Who else? Yo Shmo is going
to be prosperous? Like of course Israel's going to be prosperous. אכלי
להו? achli lehu? No. לאפוקי מדרבי הלל, l'apukei m'de'Rabbi Hillel, he's saying
this to make a point that he rejects what הלל Hillel says,
דאמר רבי הלל, d'amar Rabbi Hillel, because רבי הלל Rabbi Hillel said,
דאמר, who said, אין משיח לישראל שכבר אכלוהו בימי חזקיהו. ein Mashiach
l'Yisrael shekvar achluhu b'imei Chizkiyahu. Look at that, buried in all of
this גמרא about all this Messianic theory we have one אמורא Amora
who basically says there's no longer going to be a משיח because
all the promises of משיח were fulfilled by חזקיה המלך. Chizkiyahu HaMelech.
What does it mean no משיח?
We just don't benefit anything from it? And by רש"י there's no
משיח. רש"י says it was already נתקיים nitkayem by חזקיה המלך. Chizkiyahu
HaMelech. Okay, so so therefore I mean will there still be an
עולם הבא? Olam HaBa? Presumably, I mean it's like hard, like what's
he saying? So okay, the promises of משיח came, what's that mean?
Like is there still going to be a time when God's going
to create a totally new world? It's it's very unclear, like what
does it do to this entire פרק? perek? To this vision of
the future? But if you just look at רש"י, right, and we'll
end with this.
Where's רש"י?
Top of the left-hand column he says אין משיח לישראל, ein Mashiach
l'Yisrael, not top, like eight lines down to the narrow lines, שחזקיה
היה משיח, she'Chizkiya haya Mashiach, דהיו להם כל נבואות המתנבאות לנחמות ישראל
עמד וראה באותם השעות de'hayu lahem kol nevuot hamitnabot l'nechamot Yisrael amad
v'ra'ah b'otam hasha'ot etc. etc.
Okay
so anyway, is it going to be an עולם הבא? Olam HaBa?
Like is there going to be a תחיית המתים? t'chiyat hameitim? Like
who knows? Okay so anyway, and this is also very interesting I
should say for people that study the whole question about dogma, right,
because if you say like somebody who doesn't believe in משיח is
an אפיקורוס, apikorus, right, so what does that mean? Was הלל, Hillel,
was this רבי הלל Rebbi Hillel an אפיקורוס? apikorus? When he said
it it was okay, but after it was פסקed pasken that there
is a משיח לישראל, Mashiach l'Yisrael, then to say such a thing
would make him an אפיקורוס. apikorus. Can you פסק pasken dogma? Or
is dogma just a fact? There's just a reality. There is or
it is. So that's like a fascinating question of whether issues about
אמונה... emuna... Can be פסקן *paskened* or not פסקן
*paskened* because here they're debated, right? Do we really believe in this
or not? Is meant, is אין בין ימות עולם הזה לימות המשיח
אלא שעבוד מלכויות *ein bein yemos olam hazeh liyemos ha'Moshiach ela shibbud
malkhuyos*, שמואל *Shmuel*'s position. Like, can you פסקן *pasken* issues of אמונה
*emunah*? Is a fascinating question. I will leave you to grapple with
that. We'll end here.
Yeah, he throws this into the רמב"ם *Rambam*'s principles.